<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Paulo Scatena</title>
    <link>http://www.scatena.tv/blog/tags/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Paulo Scatena</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2016 13:50:46 -0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.scatena.tv/blog/tags/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>“It’s a new dawn…</title>
      <link>http://www.scatena.tv/blog/2016/01/16/its-a-new-dawn</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2016 13:50:46 -0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.scatena.tv/blog/2016/01/16/its-a-new-dawn</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;…It’s a new day / It’s a new life”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And… it’s here. A new blog. A new website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a couple of months years of procrastination, it’s done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is supposed to be the home of updates on my projects and, hopefully, useful insights / references / tools / scripts / whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first one being: &lt;strong&gt;creating your blog and/or site changes you&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All those “847 Reasons You Should Have a Website/Blog” articles (probably) are right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You &lt;strong&gt;should&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you don’t own a business or you don’t think it’s worth it. There is one main thing it will force you to do:
&lt;strong&gt;Revisit yourself&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you want to have a virtual business-card or to blog periodically, you’ll have to think about your content over and over. This alone will make you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Think about your goals and motivations&lt;/strong&gt;. And you might be surprised to see how much we drift from our early goals over the years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Come up with better ways of expressing yourself&lt;/strong&gt;. Work those rusty communication muscles!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get in contact with the core of your opinions&lt;/strong&gt;. We further explore our values when we actually hear our inner voices, write them down and try to explain it all to others (don’t overthink it, though).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be more organized about your stuff&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s like living alone and finding out you’ll have visit. Fastest cleaning up ever!  Having a website, even if you don’t plan on marketing it, is opening yourself to visitors. And we (usually) want to look clean and tidy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know having a website doesn’t sound that great to most people. I sure had my doubts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My inner procrastinator tried his best finding reasons why I shouldn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here it is. Here I am.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.scatena.tv/img/blog/new_thumb.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Hiya!&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And it sure was nice of you to pass by. (:&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>