<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Paulo Scatena</title>
    <link>http://www.scatena.tv/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Paulo Scatena</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2016 13:50:46 -0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.scatena.tv/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Joy of Subtle Successes</title>
      <link>http://www.scatena.tv/blog/2016/02/07/the-joy-of-subtle-successes</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2016 13:50:46 -0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.scatena.tv/blog/2016/02/07/the-joy-of-subtle-successes</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We all have our little side projects&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a DIY enthusiast, I’ve had my share. Be it redecorating a wall, designing a lamp, building a bookshelf, or even creating a website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some were needed, some were decorative. Some were completely unplanned. I once landed in a workshop and learned how to craft a fiddle. &lt;a href=&#34;https://phscatena.files.wordpress.com/2016/02/mortchego.jpg&#34;&gt;Mortchego&lt;/a&gt;, my bat puppet, was also born out of sheer opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several little projects were done just like this. Some ended up decent, some ended up great. And some were complete garbage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I felt oddly &lt;strong&gt;proud&lt;/strong&gt; of them all. More than that: I felt &lt;strong&gt;successful&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a matter of fact, those little (and perhaps pointless) tasks made me feel more successful than I felt about &lt;strong&gt;my own life&lt;/strong&gt; and career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeez.. I wonder why would that be? Why would random, unrelated projects feel so rewarding?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purpose? Possibly. But we’ve all felt successful doing something just for the sake of it at one point or another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe it all has to with &lt;strong&gt;how&lt;/strong&gt; we approach things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These “single-shot” projects act as little bubbles: standalone structures where we operate on a very functional mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It encapsulates &lt;strong&gt;everything&lt;/strong&gt; beneficial for a positive attitude and a successful output:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Involvement&lt;/strong&gt; – You personally want to see it happen…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus&lt;/strong&gt; – …and you’re willing to work on it…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Persistence&lt;/strong&gt; – …until you call it done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Associated with a very &lt;strong&gt;clear objective&lt;/strong&gt; and an often restricted time span.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, it comes from &lt;strong&gt;one single idea&lt;/strong&gt; or concept, usually not very complicated nor hard to grasp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it will almost always generate &lt;strong&gt;value&lt;/strong&gt;, as little as it might be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you do some research on the &lt;strong&gt;secret of success&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/talks/richard_st_john_s_8_secrets_of_success&#34;&gt;like this one&lt;/a&gt;), you can see why it’s easy to feel successful with simple side projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question now becomes: why is it &lt;strong&gt;harder&lt;/strong&gt; to feel successful about our life in general?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hypothesis would be that little projects, encapsulated as they are, have its concept of success more roundly defined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easier to understand. It is easier to &lt;strong&gt;achieve&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we humans have difficulty grasping a concept we haven’t defined (read &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.businessinsider.com/what-is-blue-and-how-do-we-see-color-2015-2&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; if you disagree).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As there is no global definition of success, we are in danger of following the expectations of others or running around in random directions. We ought to find &lt;strong&gt;our own&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I our side projects might help us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We just have to expand its encapsulated concept to our own careers, to our main projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One subtle step at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>“It’s a new dawn…</title>
      <link>http://www.scatena.tv/blog/2016/01/16/its-a-new-dawn</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2016 13:50:46 -0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.scatena.tv/blog/2016/01/16/its-a-new-dawn</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;…It’s a new day / It’s a new life”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And… it’s here. A new blog. A new website.
After a couple of months years of procrastination, it’s done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is supposed to be the home of updates on my projects and, hopefully, useful insights / references / tools / scripts / whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first one being: &lt;strong&gt;creating your blog and/or site changes you&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All those “847 Reasons You Should Have a Website/Blog” articles (probably) are right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You &lt;strong&gt;should&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you don’t own a business or you don’t think it’s worth it. There is one main thing it will force you to do:
&lt;strong&gt;Revisit yourself&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you want to have a virtual business-card or to blog periodically, you’ll have to think about your content over and over. This alone will make you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Think about your goals and motivations&lt;/strong&gt;. And you might be surprised to see how much we drift from our early goals over the years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Come up with better ways of expressing yourself&lt;/strong&gt;. Work those rusty communication muscles!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get in contact with the core of your opinions&lt;/strong&gt;. We further explore our values when we actually hear our inner voices, write them down and try to explain it all to others (don’t overthink it, though).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be more organized about your stuff&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s like living alone and finding out you’ll have visit. Fastest cleaning up ever!  Having a website, even if you don’t plan on marketing it, is opening yourself to visitors. And we (usually) want to look clean and tidy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know having a website doesn’t sound that great to most people. I sure had my doubts.
My inner procrastinator tried his best finding reasons why I shouldn’t.
It could &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here it is. Here I am.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://phscatena.files.wordpress.com/2016/01/thumb_200px.jpg?w=660&#34; alt=&#34;Hiya!&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And it sure was nice of you to pass by. (:&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>