<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thoughts on Paulo Scatena</title>
    <link>http://www.scatena.tv/blog/categories/thoughts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Thoughts on Paulo Scatena</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2016 17:02:13 -0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.scatena.tv/blog/categories/thoughts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Bouncing Ball - A shortcut to keen eyes</title>
      <link>http://www.scatena.tv/blog/2016/03/25/bouncing-ball---a-shortcut-to-keen-eyes</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2016 17:02:13 -0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.scatena.tv/blog/2016/03/25/bouncing-ball---a-shortcut-to-keen-eyes</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The most basic animation exercise is the bouncing ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Literally &lt;strong&gt;basic&lt;/strong&gt;, because it involves the most fundamental, most interesting, most robust, most sensual unit of all universe:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.scatena.tv/img/blog/bouncing_escher.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;SPHERE&lt;/strong&gt; (according to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HVXEi1BYmXQ&#34;&gt;science&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animators, those restless creatures, put the sphere in motion. That&amp;rsquo;s how bouncing balls are born. Poetic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this little ball, fundamental as it is, often becomes just an exercise and is left behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great animators never forget about it, and its principles are apparent in their scenes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But no one is born great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most animators are too busy with everything they need to get right: poses, silhouettes, arcs, anticipations, overlap, constraints etc etc etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what you see most in animation is just..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;good-enough:64362d7a43b71d3a1ea4ef5d1189b67d&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Good enough&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every animator has once reached a moment when his scene works, his friends and family think it&amp;rsquo;s super cool, but his fellow animators give that look of &amp;lsquo;it is.. well.. &lt;em&gt;OK&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did a lot of work under extremely thigh deadlines, using motion capture, and I felt that everything I delivered was never great. It was just &amp;ldquo;good enough.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;m stubborn and wanted to be great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A year ago, on a workshop at iAnimate, I started a scene. I had time and wanted it to be &lt;strong&gt;great&lt;/strong&gt;. But I noticed that I didn&amp;rsquo;t even know how to do it. My eyes were too accustomed to the &amp;ldquo;good enough&amp;rdquo; standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I saw the light. Right in this &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/121632004&#34;&gt;video here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trent Corey is an amazing animator. His drawings are great, so it was no surprise to see that he begins his scene with &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;drafts&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I saw how he blocks it out: he uses a 3D bouncing ball, which by itself feel alive: it conveys intention and emotion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then realized that if you can breath life into a bouncing ball, you can breath life into &lt;strong&gt;anything&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;finding-what-s-essential:64362d7a43b71d3a1ea4ef5d1189b67d&#34;&gt;Finding what&amp;rsquo;s essential&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple character has: a hip, a chest, a head, two legs and two arms. Already you have seven things to pay attention to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, where to start, where to go?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can eliminate this doubt by leaving only &lt;strong&gt;one&lt;/strong&gt;  thing to look at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simplifying, you get in touch with what is most &lt;strong&gt;essential&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you&amp;rsquo;re nearer to its essence, you can act where it &lt;strong&gt;matters&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;video autoplay loop muted controls&gt;&lt;source type=&#34;video/mp4&#34; src=&#34;http://www.scatena.tv/vid/blog/bouncing_demo.mp4&#34;&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;center-altering-choreography-and-rhythm-via-a-bouncing-ball-center:64362d7a43b71d3a1ea4ef5d1189b67d&#34;&gt;&lt;center&gt; Altering choreography and rhythm via a bouncing ball &lt;/center&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-s-easy-is-mediocre:64362d7a43b71d3a1ea4ef5d1189b67d&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s easy is mediocre&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a director says &amp;lsquo;make this character happy!&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easiest thing to do it to throw a big smile at it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.scatena.tv/img/blog/bouncing_yay.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Yaaay!&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Try it yourself: &lt;em&gt;look&lt;/em&gt; happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now make that grin disappear and try again. Can you feel your body looking for ways to express itself? The neck straightens, the chest opens &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you walk with that attitude, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably be lighter and more confident. Even without a smile, or even without holding a pose, people will know that you are happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Movement&lt;/strong&gt; speaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s what matters most here. It is what matters to us animators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do the movement &lt;strong&gt;tells a story&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking for these solutions will be less obvious, more difficult. And for that same reason, it will be much more interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;video autoplay loop muted controls&gt;&lt;source type=&#34;video/mp4&#34; src=&#34;http://www.scatena.tv/vid/blog/bouncing_balls.mp4&#34;&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;center-to-each-ball-its-own-story-center:64362d7a43b71d3a1ea4ef5d1189b67d&#34;&gt;&lt;center&gt; To each ball its own story &lt;/center&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;keep-it-simple:64362d7a43b71d3a1ea4ef5d1189b67d&#34;&gt;Keep it simple&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew an animator who always worried too much about details, while the essence of his scenes were weak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when directed to focus on what mattered, this guy still got lost. As soon as the supervisor asked for a stronger pose, a fear of messing something up and getting it worse would pop up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That guy was me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing back the bouncing ball, physically, proved itself to be a way to faster develop the critical eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes it easier to &lt;strong&gt;feel&lt;/strong&gt; what can be improved. And there is less fear of pushing the animation and exploring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus, the scene is lighter with just a ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So use of the bouncing ball to avoid distractions: forget about that elbow crossing the mesh, those curled up fingers, that foot being left behind, those cross-eyed gaze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this stuff steal your attention; it takes away your focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bouncing ball is impassive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;rsquo;s your friend. Let it help you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;video autoplay loop muted controls&gt;&lt;source type=&#34;video/mp4&#34; src=&#34;http://www.scatena.tv/vid/blog/bouncing_badmocap1.mp4&#34;&gt;&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;video autoplay loop muted controls&gt;&lt;source type=&#34;video/mp4&#34; src=&#34;http://www.scatena.tv/vid/blog/bouncing_badmocap2.mp4&#34;&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;center-using-the-bouncing-ball-to-turn-bad-mocap-into-something-more-interesting-center:64362d7a43b71d3a1ea4ef5d1189b67d&#34;&gt;&lt;center&gt; Using the bouncing ball to turn bad mocap into something more interesting &lt;/center&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;two-steps-forward-one-step-back:64362d7a43b71d3a1ea4ef5d1189b67d&#34;&gt;Two steps forward, one step back&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those starting from a blank scene it is easy, maybe natural, to keep in mind the essence of the movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with the increased use of mocap, it is required from the animator highly developed eyes - knowing precisely what to use and what to throw away. Something that can only come through experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So adding the bouncing ball to the scene may look like extra work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t have time for this.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you don&amp;rsquo;t have time for is to fix 30 poses on a character with 47 controllers just to realize you&amp;rsquo;re left with a dull scene in your hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This laziness to take a step back and see the big picture is what makes most of recent animation to look generic, lifeless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is increasingly easier to get good references (mocap or video), and it is up to the animator to convey his vision, to add some spices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bouncing ball is a way to explore faster, to see what&amp;rsquo;s wrong faster, to correct it faster, to &lt;strong&gt;improve&lt;/strong&gt; faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It helps you to let go of worries and to become free to dare &amp;ndash; and this is something good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manage to convey the core emotion of your scene with a simple bouncing ball, it will make the final result so much stronger and so much more enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#### It is just a tool&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bouncing ball is no magic answer to anything. But it is something at your disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; made great improvements on my &lt;strong&gt;feel&lt;/strong&gt; for good animation going back to the most fundamental animation exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;ve used this method with some colleagues who were learning and noticed a clear progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must keep in mind that it is only part of the process. Something that &lt;strong&gt;can&lt;/strong&gt; help and &lt;strong&gt;shouldn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/strong&gt; take too long. The bouncing ball is a shortcut to what is essential, not a tortuous detour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I vote for the return of the bouncing ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let&amp;rsquo;s add details later.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heaven&#39;s Nest - A Subtle Success</title>
      <link>http://www.scatena.tv/blog/2016/03/02/heavens-nest---a-subtle-success</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2016 19:25:55 -0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.scatena.tv/blog/2016/03/02/heavens-nest---a-subtle-success</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I wrote about subtle successes due to the last one that struck me: &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/150454094&#34;&gt;Heaven&amp;rsquo;s Nest&lt;/a&gt;. Through creating this short 2D animation I relearned everything I knew about creative processes. I&amp;rsquo;ll use it as a case study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-context:c76e05b769f6cf6962f66c91f4377a94&#34;&gt;The Context&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was December and I was exhausted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had spent the last few months exploring the possibilities on the future of animation &amp;ndash; a very, very broad field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I needed a vacation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I stumbled upon December&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.11secondclub.com/&#34;&gt;11 Second Club&lt;/a&gt;. Hearing that excerpt, I sensed inside of me a very strong emotional response, beyond rationality. A physical impulse to create!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The year has been quite chaotic, with ups and downs I had never experienced before. To be able to create an animation from that emotional response was a chance to catalyze the mixture of all that I had been experiencing: animation and new technologies, studies of the body through physical theater, and my emotions at the moment!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-process:c76e05b769f6cf6962f66c91f4377a94&#34;&gt;The Process&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That same day I tried to externalize what I felt hearing the sound file, letting my body lead explore what could then become scene. I did not worry about anything, just leaving a camera running.
A flying gesture soon appeared, and I realized the character was a bird who lost its offspring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watching the video, I tried to feel the energy of the scene, and I also picked some poses that I considered important, that &lt;strong&gt;told a story&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.scatena.tv/img/blog/heavens_vidref.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Video reference: farewell, dignity&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From there, I did rough drawing to visualize how it could all be staged. Do note its draftsmanship quality.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.scatena.tv/img/blog/heavens_roughs.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;First rough sketches&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t concerned at that moment about the character, whatever it was &amp;ndash; bird, human, or something in between. I was concerned with its, the &lt;strong&gt;intention&lt;/strong&gt; of its movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I soon noticed that I was taking to long trying to make advances drawing in 2D. So I turned back to 3D and animated a bouncing ball¹ so I could define its timing and flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video autoplay=&#34;1&#34; loop=&#34;1&#34; muted&gt;&lt;source type=&#34;video/mp4&#34; src=&#34;http://www.scatena.tv/vid/blog/heavens_ball12fps.mp4&#34;&gt;&lt;/video&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I began exploring the bird&amp;rsquo;s design. With some references, I&amp;rsquo;ve got to this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.scatena.tv/img/blog/heavens_bird.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Character design&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My idea was using this project as a way to test a to test a water-colored animation style, trying to achieve a delicate lightness, as I had done before in an illustrated letter to a very dear person, who I&amp;rsquo;d like to honor here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I also liked the idea of ​​working with paper and ink, and not screens and wires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished the jobs I had, and as I prepared to finally dive into this project, a sore throat made me feverish and knocked me down. When I felt better, I had the urge to disconnect from technology, and traveled to the coast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent those days studying birds - both from video and real life, including the fortunate sight of a woodpecker and a toucan. I used this time to also explore &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scatena.tv/img/blog/heavens_paint.jpg&#34;&gt;watercolor styles&lt;/a&gt; as well.
It was also a time for watching references, especially the classic &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0057546/&#34;&gt;The Sword in the Stone&lt;/a&gt; (old owl Archimedes is still one of my favorite characters).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I returned home with only eight days left to the deadline. I began animating the bird&amp;rsquo;s body, but realized I was easily losing the focus &amp;ndash; exploring the background, colors, lines, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the rush I had, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have enough time &lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt; to plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I made a daily schedule, which went something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;25dez - improve body and feet; draw head 4s;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;26dez - wings on 4s;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;27dez - &amp;ldquo;beaksync&amp;rdquo;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;28dez - draw all on 2s;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;29dez - painting - 6 min max. per drawing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;30dez - finish painting;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;31dez - render and upload&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some tasks were more difficult than I anticipated (eg. defining the wings&amp;rsquo; movement), and to top it off, I got an ear infection, leaving me a couple of days behind schedule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I noticed that progress was being made and not on one day had I have to work to the point of exhaustion: I took breaks, watched movies, slept well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 30th, however, the animation was at decent shape, but I figured I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have time for painting. In the excitement of this final stretch, I didn&amp;rsquo;t sleept and just kept working. In the morning, the unpainted animation was completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the day I noticed it was wise to separate a day for rendering: dealing with so many layers, passes, and an absurdly high resolution was slow and laborious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 5PM everything was ready. I was satisfied, but not completely. The project included painting. The original idea was watercolor with no outlines, and all I had were outlines. So I got whatever energy was left in me and started painting.. But with 183 frames, each part of the bird took me around 40 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was past 11PM when I uploaded the final version and left to some friends&amp;rsquo; New Year&amp;rsquo;s party.
And I was completely satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-result:c76e05b769f6cf6962f66c91f4377a94&#34;&gt;The Result&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feedback I got at 11 Second Club was not very good, and more than one person questioned whether it was rotoscoped (I wonder what would the original material be; I have yet to see such dramatic bird). Also, after some time away from the scene, I began to think that the outline animation had more appeal than the painted version (which originated some good discussions with fellow animators).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was very &lt;strong&gt;proud&lt;/strong&gt; of having done this scene. All things considered, it was an achievement for me. I&amp;rsquo;ve done it all in eight days (plus pre-prod) and faced two diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was something that made me a satisfaction similar to the one I had upon completing &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/21672106&#34;&gt;Blackout&lt;/a&gt;, my first short film that preceded my studies in animation, and was done with a pleasant discipline that I rarely reproduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s when I thought ..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would projects that I &amp;ldquo;just did&amp;rdquo; happened while pretentious, calculated projects studied do not get off the ground?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve produced less content in the years following my graduation in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.animationmentor.com/&#34;&gt;Animation Mentor&lt;/a&gt; than in previous years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe, from the point where I started to educate myself, my requirement levels grew. Meaning: I needed to be &lt;strong&gt;ready&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The projects I envisioned seemed huge, and required vast experience. So I&amp;rsquo;d first need to develop myself to be good enough. And then one day I&amp;rsquo;d feel comfortable to dive in. Would I really?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it&amp;rsquo;s often said in entrepreneurship: If you&amp;rsquo;re feeling comfortable, you took too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not feel ready to make Heaven&amp;rsquo;s Nest. And I do not think it is a great achievement in 2D animation. Nor Blackout, as a short movie. Both have plenty of mistakes and great room for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But both &lt;strong&gt;happened&lt;/strong&gt;, and were achievements for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today I&amp;rsquo;m more concerned on completing &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;minor&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;, perhaps less pretentious, projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But those which call for this &lt;strong&gt;urgency&lt;/strong&gt;, the ones which I feel I &lt;strong&gt;can not NOT DO&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s not aiming lower - not at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is having the conscience that one can only climb higher with the support of small successive achievements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in a way, that means enjoying more the climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facing the unique challenge of each step - and celebrating its success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;¹ I&amp;rsquo;ll write more about this bouncing ball workflow in an upcoming post.&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Joy of Subtle Successes</title>
      <link>http://www.scatena.tv/blog/2016/02/07/the-joy-of-subtle-successes</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2016 13:50:46 -0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.scatena.tv/blog/2016/02/07/the-joy-of-subtle-successes</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We all have our little side projects&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a DIY enthusiast, I’ve had my share. Be it redecorating a wall, designing a lamp, building a bookshelf, or even creating a website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some were needed, some were decorative. Some were completely unplanned. I once landed in a workshop and learned how to craft a fiddle. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scatena.tv/img/blog/subtle_mortchego.jpg&#34;&gt;Mortchego&lt;/a&gt;, my bat puppet, was also born out of sheer opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several little projects were done just like this. Some ended up decent, some ended up great. And some were complete garbage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I felt oddly &lt;strong&gt;proud&lt;/strong&gt; of them all. More than that: I felt &lt;strong&gt;successful&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a matter of fact, those little (and perhaps pointless) tasks made me feel more successful than I felt about &lt;strong&gt;my own life&lt;/strong&gt; and career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeez.. I wonder why would that be? Why would random, unrelated projects feel so rewarding?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purpose? Possibly. But we’ve all felt successful doing something just for the sake of it at one point or another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe it all has to with &lt;strong&gt;how&lt;/strong&gt; we approach things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These “single-shot” projects act as little bubbles: standalone structures where we operate on a very functional mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It encapsulates &lt;strong&gt;everything&lt;/strong&gt; beneficial for a positive attitude and a successful output:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Involvement&lt;/strong&gt; – You personally want to see it happen…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus&lt;/strong&gt; – …and you’re willing to work on it…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Persistence&lt;/strong&gt; – …until you call it done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Associated with a very &lt;strong&gt;clear objective&lt;/strong&gt; and an often restricted time span.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, it comes from &lt;strong&gt;one single idea&lt;/strong&gt; or concept, usually not very complicated nor hard to grasp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it will almost always generate &lt;strong&gt;value&lt;/strong&gt;, as little as it might be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you do some research on the &lt;strong&gt;secret of success&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/talks/richard_st_john_s_8_secrets_of_success&#34;&gt;like this one&lt;/a&gt;), you can see why it’s easy to feel successful with simple side projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question now becomes: why is it &lt;strong&gt;harder&lt;/strong&gt; to feel successful about our life in general?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hypothesis would be that little projects, encapsulated as they are, have its concept of success more roundly defined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easier to understand. It is easier to &lt;strong&gt;achieve&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we humans have difficulty grasping a concept we haven’t defined (read &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.businessinsider.com/what-is-blue-and-how-do-we-see-color-2015-2&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; if you disagree).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As there is no global definition of success, we are in danger of following the expectations of others or running around in random directions. We ought to find &lt;strong&gt;our own&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I our side projects might help us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We just have to expand its encapsulated concept to our own careers, to our main projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One subtle step at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>“It’s a new dawn…</title>
      <link>http://www.scatena.tv/blog/2016/01/16/its-a-new-dawn</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2016 13:50:46 -0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.scatena.tv/blog/2016/01/16/its-a-new-dawn</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;…It’s a new day / It’s a new life”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And… it’s here. A new blog. A new website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a couple of months years of procrastination, it’s done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is supposed to be the home of updates on my projects and, hopefully, useful insights / references / tools / scripts / whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first one being: &lt;strong&gt;creating your blog and/or site changes you&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All those “847 Reasons You Should Have a Website/Blog” articles (probably) are right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You &lt;strong&gt;should&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you don’t own a business or you don’t think it’s worth it. There is one main thing it will force you to do:
&lt;strong&gt;Revisit yourself&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you want to have a virtual business-card or to blog periodically, you’ll have to think about your content over and over. This alone will make you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Think about your goals and motivations&lt;/strong&gt;. And you might be surprised to see how much we drift from our early goals over the years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Come up with better ways of expressing yourself&lt;/strong&gt;. Work those rusty communication muscles!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get in contact with the core of your opinions&lt;/strong&gt;. We further explore our values when we actually hear our inner voices, write them down and try to explain it all to others (don’t overthink it, though).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be more organized about your stuff&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s like living alone and finding out you’ll have visit. Fastest cleaning up ever!  Having a website, even if you don’t plan on marketing it, is opening yourself to visitors. And we (usually) want to look clean and tidy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know having a website doesn’t sound that great to most people. I sure had my doubts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My inner procrastinator tried his best finding reasons why I shouldn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here it is. Here I am.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.scatena.tv/img/blog/new_thumb.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Hiya!&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And it sure was nice of you to pass by. (:&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>